Um, are the markets right? Is it not as
bad as some people worry?
Well, it could I mean, you know, that's
the thing, right Mario? Is that we
there's so much uncertainty that it you
know, we nobody can make a definitive
statement. So, what we're really talking
about is probabilities. What are the
probabilities that we end up in say a
bad case and what are the probabilities
that we can avoid the bad case?
And the very simple calculation here is
the longer this goes, the probability
shift unfavorably, right? The higher
gasoline prices go in the US and diesel
in Europe and jet fuel across Asia, the
chances of the worst case or just bad
cases just goes up and up and up. And by
the way, the Trump administration
obviously very well aware of it, which
is why they're
they seem to be rushing. Uh, what we
don't know is that you know, there's a
point of no return here. Um, just
stepping back, looking at the big
picture historical case, energy shocks
precede recessions. And usually it's the
combination of things, but you know, you
have a relatively weak economy that's
late in a cycle. Um, you know, things
are already moving in the wrong
direction, then you know, bam, uh, oil
oil costs go up, probably sharply and
it's enough to tip everything over the
edge.
Pretty much everybody's well aware of
the risk. So, if you're a stock market
investor, or at least you think you're
stock market investor, you look at some
of the stock indexes anyway, it looks
like it what you just said. The stock
market says, we've avoided that worst
case, we haven't got to the tipping
point, the probabilities are actually
moving favorable because things are
moving in the right direction on the
geopolitical front. The you the US
administration, the US and whoever it is
over in Iran, they're going to make a
deal, they'll get everything flowing
again.
That'll be great before all the damage
gets done. However, you know, even in
the stock market, it isn't so cut and
dry because yes, the uh, you know, some
of the various stock indexes are hitting
hitting new highs, but the breadth has
been terrible, which means that a lot of
stocks people aren't really buying.
There's still a lot of nervousness even
in the equity market that may be
>> Breath means Breath means only a small
percentage of stocks that are carrying
the entire market. That's not spread
across the entire multiple industries
and and indices.
Yeah, so we we get lazy, right? We say
the stock market says everything is
fine. But what are we really saying?
What we're saying is in this case, a
very narrow slice of the stock market
says everything is fine. And that's
largely because people have moved on to
AI and you know, maybe the technology in
the in the in the for AI that's going to
benefit and there're going to be lots of
winners and lots of upside there. But
all the rest of the stock market is
still kind of hung up a little bit. It's
not all overly pessimistic to be sure,
but it isn't so rock solid hey, we've
moved past the rant. So even in the
stock market there's a significant
amount of anxiety, let's call it. That
maybe we still have to deal with some
consequences here. Then you move into
the other markets, which to me are
vastly more important. Especially when
you're talking about discounting
information. You look at something like
forward rate markets. What does the
forward rate market look like? Because
that's basically what interest rates are
going to do short-term interest rates
are going to do in the near term and
then further out. And if you would
expect us to go into, you know, to avoid
the worst case in the economic
economic consequences, avoid financial
volatility, you would expect an upward
sloping curve because that would be more
normalized.
And we're still seeing
Well, it it actually looks like a frown
right now because the market expects
central banks to raise rates a little
bit in the short run. There's a chance
that they do including the Federal
Reserve, but then have to cut rates
after
some indeterminate amount of time
relatively soon into, you know, maybe
later this year or next year, which is
not good scenarios. If the Fed say
raises its rates by 25 basis points
thinking that oil prices are
inflationary, which by the way they are
not. If they make that same mistake
that, you know, Jean-Claude Trichet made
in 2008, July of 2008 when the ECB
raised rates in the middle of the great
recession,
they're very likely to have to turn
around and and lower rates as we get
into the more unfavorable scenario.
>> hold on, oil prices going up is not
inflationary?
Oil prices have a direct impact on
consumer prices in the short run, but
they're not inflationary in the sense
that most people understand the term
inflation, which is that prices outside
of oil respond to oil and it leads to a
sustained acceleration in in broad
consumer prices, not narrow consumer
prices. Again, this is one of the
historical lessons from energy shocks.
You get a shock in consumer prices
driven by gasoline in the short run, but
then over a period of time as the
economy takes the hit, demand falls off
and prices of everything else other than
oil start to collapse and even oil
prices eventually collapse once once
enough demand is destroyed. So, what you
see is a very short run spike in the
consumer price index and then almost as
soon as it goes up, it goes right back
down again. Demand destruction, so
people just start to to to to to to
travel less, to move around less.
>> Travel or you know, look, you have less
money to spend. I mean, right now most
people most consumers, you know, they're
they're spending an extra $100, $150 a
month on gasoline. That Well, that's
money that they can't spend anywhere
else because the labor market is not
robust.
>> Mhm. And if the labor market's not
robust, they're not generating nearly
enough income to absorb the higher
energy costs, which means they have to
pull spending back from someplace else.
And it's not just consumers. Businesses
that have already been pressured for
several years now seeing their margins
erode, especially smaller medium-sized
businesses seeing their margins erode,
suddenly they get hit with a higher
diesel cost bill, what are they going to
do? They have to cut their costs
someplace else because they're not
seeing new business come in. So, where
do they cut their costs then? Well, So,
that's more recessionary. You think that
would be more recessionary rather than
inflationary. That's the real risk. So,
that's what we're talking about here
about the unfavorable outcome. How much
demand destruction takes place? Is it
too much that leads into where we put
where businesses pull back too much to
the point that they're not just cutting
costs, they end up cutting workers. Then
that leads to a higher degree of layoffs
or higher number of layoffs, higher
unemployment, and suddenly what looked
like it was going to be inflation to
most people, especially central bankers,
ends up being the historical
recessionary case. So, that's what we're
trying to figure out. What is the
balanced probability on both sides?
So, what happens let's see let's use a
few hypotheticals. What happens if oil
hits $200, the number that everyone's
been throwing around? And I know we're
not there yet, but if we see a
continuation of the war, if we look at
the the worst case scenario. I was on a
on a show with one of the negotiate one
of the three advisers to the negotiators
in Iran earlier today. And um
you know, he was very pessimistic on how
things are going. He's like, "Mario, the
military build-up
shows that war is almost inevitable
despite Trump seemingly wanting to walk
away." Um so, if we do see a
continuation of the war and we see a you
know, a sig- maybe the closure of the
Strait of Hormuz for the rest of the
year. Oh, god. I'm thinking really bad
case scenario. Yeah, what would that
look like? That would be catastrophic.
Um you know, I I tend to agree with that
that analysis. Um I think this is a much
longer affair. And I've said this from
the very beginning. This is not going to
be a 6-week thing. This is I mean
>> Oh, really? Yeah, I think the Trump
administration is in it for the they're
not going to back down until they get
what they want. Now, we don't really
know what they want. I mean, they've
said basically we want the nuclear
program erased. Um I think they probably
want regime change and regime collapse
in Iran. I think they're managing
expectations to try to keep the market
from turning catastrophic in the short
run.
Why do you think they want regime
change? Is it to control the Strait of
Hormuz for leverage over China?
I think this is all about China. It goes
back to the Cold War II.
So,
you you know, Panama Canal, Venezuela,
Cuba, Greenland, this is not about Iran
or Israel. It's about China. It's about
countering it's it's about putting
yourself in a Cold War mindset except
the primary adversary is no longer the
Soviet Union. It's now the Chinese.
And the Chinese have taken a number of
provocative steps already. I mean, uh we
hear I mean, every every every other
every other day there's some news story
about the Chinese doing something inside
the US. Whether attacking some kind of
system, buying farmland up next to US
military bases, especially where our
bombers are located. I mean, a lot of
provocative stuff. I think the Trump
administration came into office and came
into this latest minute of the second
Trump term saying, "We've got to do
something about China. We can no longer
just sit here and do nothing." And
that's where this done road doctrine
came from. We start with defending the
Western Hemisphere, but also sending a
message to China
as well as all those who might be
considering lining up with China to say,
"Look, they can't protect you. We're
going into a binary sort of world where
it's You know, I hate to use the term
cuz it's associated with the Bush
administration, but it's us versus them
kind of a thing." And Iran is a huge
piece in that in that um Cold War
calculus.
So, toppling the re or the Iranian
regime would be of huge piece. Um
there's all sorts of other
you know, benefits that go along with
it. So, I think the Trump administration
has has decided, at least that's what it
looks like to me,
um whatever the short-run consequences
are, it's worth the long-run gain if
they can pull it off and execute it,
which by the way is a huge if. There's
no guarantee in any of that. So, what
are the short-run consequences? You're
right, Mario.
If the Hormuz if the Strait of Hormuz
continues to be closed for much longer,
I mean, oil prices are not that far from
$200 as it is. The cash price of oil is
like 130, 140. It's been as high as 150.
That's already happened. Now, reason
most people don't see that is because
the futures price of oil is down around
$100 per barrel. And that has been
heavily manipulated through administer
the you know, administration track
tactics. Um every time oil the futures
price of oil starts to creep up, what
happens? Trump will come out with a
Truth Social that says, Well, Barack
"Hey, expect your speech by tomorrow."
Yeah, or you you know, I've there's
there's a uh big speech coming up in 2
days and you don't want to be long oil
in that case. So, they have done a
masterful job manipulating the futures
price of oil. You got to tip your cap to
them in that respect. They have kept the
lid on the futures price of oil. how
However, economic reality is economic
reality. It's cold, it's brutal, and the
truth of the matter is there's so much
oil that is being constrained, just an
absolutely incomprehensible amount. Um
it was the uh
the head of the International Energy
Agency who said this is 1973, 1979, and
2022 combined.
So, the reason why it doesn't
>> 2022, 1979, and what? 1973.
So, all three of the major energy shocks
of my lifetime um combined. That's the
amount of oil that's being constrained
through Hormuz. The reason it doesn't
feel that way is because first of all,
the futures price of oil has largely
been manipulated and stable, so it
doesn't look like it's all that I mean
the you know, WTI is well below where it
was in 2022. Doesn't look all that bad.
And the other thing is the system does
have some margin to absorb. We've got
inventories that are floating around cuz
remember we were talking about a supply
glut globally before we started with the
Iran conflict. So, there was there's oil
inventories out there. They've been able
to work around the bottleneck in the
Strait to a certain extent. Um their
strategic reserves have helped a little
bit, but the capacity to absorb that
level of shock is running dry and it's
getting closer and closer to ending,
which means
as much as as successful as they've been
at manipulating the future price of oil,
it's going to start to converge with the
cash price. Like I said, the cash price
is already astronomically high to begin
with, and so we've already seen
>> is essentially what what anyone buying
oil what they pay for it now on the
market. So, if if if you if you're
you're you're you're you're country and
want to buy some of the barrels of oil
floating around, that's how much cash
you pay right now. That's what you would
pay right now for a specific cargo
that's leaving in a specific place for a
specific grade of oil. So, what is the
cash price
>> for it, isn't it? There's like a name
for it in the market like something
crude, I remember. The thing is there's
no single oil price. The The one that
people have been throwing around is
called Dated Brent, which is sort of a
Yeah, so there are a lots of different
prices of oil, and usually it doesn't
matter because they're usually
relatively the same range, but in this
case they've diverged historically, you
know, historic fashion so that the cash
price is ridiculously high. So what
happens is over time, the real these
real economic fundamentals have to
converge with reality. So as much as
Trump has been successful manipulating
futures price, gasoline we've seen this
rise in the United States. Wholesale
gasoline, which is still a futures
price, but wholesale gasoline on April
17th was $3 per gallon. And $3 per
gallon roughly translates into a retail
price of around 4 to 425. So already not
good. $4 gasoline not good. But the
futures price of gasoline, which is
called RBOB, went from $3 a gallon to as
high as 375 in just a couple of weeks as
the gasoline market is first of all
inventories have dropped precipitously
because a lot of fuel is being shipped
off to Asia where it's really in in
short supply, but also because, you
know, um you know, the cash price is is
that economic reality starting to exert
itself in the futures market. So
you get a futures price of gasoline in
the United States of 375,
that's $5 per per gallon US retail
gasoline. Nationwide average, not just
in California or Oregon, nationwide
average of $5 gasoline. That's where we
are right now. If nothing changes, if
absolutely nothing changes, we're on
we're on track for $5 per gallon
gasoline Politically that makes
everything horrible for Trump and from a
political perspective as well for the
midterms.
Yes, so I think I honestly think the
Trump administration has probably
correctly said the midterms are lost
cause. Um so if we think the Iran
conflict is worth the end goal, we'll
sacrifice the midterms, maybe even the
economy along the way. And And you know,
uh it's maybe in some respects it's hard
to argue with that calculus because Iran
having a nuclear weapon is is the very
definition of catastrophe. So if that's
really the case, then I think they have
said, "Look, we're We're to sacrifice
the short run
>> I think but the the the the China
argument makes a lot more a lot more
sense than the nuclear weapons argument.
I think Iran has shown through the
JCPOA, through the Oman negotiations
that they're willing to give up their
nuclear ambitions as long as they get
some economic relief as well, some of
the sanctions lifted. That's been a
pretty clear position on their front.
That's why for me the nuclear argument
doesn't make sense. And
generally speaking, almost every single
war, whatever reason is given to the
public is not the real reason for the
war. It's the one that makes more the
most political sense. Um I think the
argument that the
>> it smarter. That's what makes this
analysis more difficult cuz we don't
know. We're we're we're, you know, we
always have, you know,
perfect information.
Why did they attack Iraq? Very briefly,
what do you think it is? What what
happened? What what led to the Iraq war?
Cuz I think economics I think economics
is probably plays the biggest role in
dictating politics.
I think in this case the Bush
administration said, "We're going to
have a war with Islamic terrorists. It's
better to have it over there than over
here."
And so they just picked a spot on the
map and said, "Let's fight them in
Iraq." I think that's what that's where
they were wrong.
>> No, I don't think it was about oil. I
think there was no reason to fight for
oil back then. Yes, oil prices had risen
from the late 1990s. You could argue
that it contributed to the dot-com
recession in 2001, but I think it was
really about uh 9/11. Uh honestly, I
think that what what the Bush
administration said in all wars,
uh the the
the side that picks where you fight more
often has the biggest advantage.
>> [clears throat]
>> Hm. I think if that's the case, then he
would have been misled. Cuz that one
just doesn't make sense if it's about
fighting extremism. Okay, but then let's
let's bring it to the scenario here, uh
the war against China. Uh sorry, the war
against Iran. Um Hopefully not.
>> So, it is all about China. The war it is
about the the indirect war that the the
cold war with China.
Um
That's it. Because I've been saying So,
I made a post that went viral making
that exact point that everyone's talking
about Israel Israel nuclear program.
Well, guys, I I think it's about China
controlling the energy choke points
around the world cuz China has rare
earth. We need to have something or the
West needs something or the US needs
something to to to to kind of counter
that that leverage card that China has.
And now base I've also been saying those
things contradict one another. I've been
saying that the war is
since early April um yeah, early April I
was saying the war is about to end. And
since the ceasefire I've said guys, it's
over. There is no way Trump can continue
this war. But then this clashes with
what I've been saying if it it is about
China then this is worth losing the
midterms from a strategic long-term
perspective. Um
Yeah, so what worries me is that uh I
don't know.
What worries me the most is that, you
know, there seems to be a little bit of
urgency here because the Trump
administration went from one to the next
to the next to the next almost in in
rapid sequence, right? And there's a
strategy here. This is not willy-nilly.
This is not something they just dreamed
up overnight and said, oh, we're going
to go attack Venezuela. Um there is a
definitely a strategy here that's being
carried out. What worries me is that the
Trump administration is responding to
specific threats. Whether that be about
China attacking Taiwan or something
closer to home, I don't know. Just
speculating, but it seems like there's a
there is a high degree of urgency in
moving from one to the next to the next.
And you know, as as the administration
officials have indicated, as soon as
they wrap up in Iran, it looks like
they're going to be starting with Cuba.
It's one after another after another.
And I think it comes down to um yeah,
economics is part of it, but I think
it's just pure power politics, right? Um
it's sending a message to basically the
rest of the world that, you know, we are
realigning the the planet in a lot of
different ways. And if you think you are
thinking of aligning with China, look
what happened to Maduro. Look what
happened to maybe what the regime in
Cuba. Look what happened to Iran, which,
you know, Iran and China were supposed
to be really tight. Um the Chinese can't
really protect you and you either get
with the program or you don't get with
the program. That seems to me the
overarching uh strategy here is to
realign everything. Perfect example, the
UAE leaving OPEC. Now the UAE has been
on the you know they've been talking
about leaving OPEC for quite some time
but they've always been kind of on the
fence and in the grand scheme of things
OPEC's importance is is diminished to
begin with but that that also goes along
with what I'm talking about here
re-aligning for the
the rest of the 21st century. It's
essentially taking the old leftovers
from the 20th century and chipping away
at them and and redrawing the lines on
the map to something else and the UAE is
an important symbolic
shift in that direction. They're pulling
out of OPEC. They're real they're
aligning themselves even closer to the
United States which is a symbolic
symbolic move in that direction because
it's I think it fits the overall
political strategy here.
That is really interesting that they're
bringing the UAE into this cuz that
a lot of people are talking about
countries re-aligning away from the US
cuz the US dragged the Gulf into this
war unnecessarily. Um the US bases are
seen as a liability. Some countries
might question the alliance with the US
cuz you know they've been thrown off
thrown into the war the the Gulf. Asia's
suffering because of the war Europe to a
lesser extent into a war that the US
decided to unilaterally launch. But
you're making the argument that guys
they might be pissed off but there's
there's also the argument that they have
no choice and the UAE is an indicator of
that. Despite the UAE being attacked
more than any other country if the
what they've done is they've doubled
down on that American partnership. So
that kind of could be an indicator of
what's to come is that we might see a
re-alignment to
towards the US rather than the opposite
because the US is more aggressive
militarily.
Or at least the US is acting in a way
that actually benefits them if even if
it isn't apparent right now. I mean the
UAE probably knows this more than
anybody but like you said they're the
ones that have been attacked primarily
even more than Israel. At least that's
you know that's the intelligence that we
have which suggests that the who is Iran
more pissed off at?
Who is who is the real enemies in the
Middle East or where are they where are
the actual fault lines in the Middle
East? You think it's you think you know
where it where they are, but I think
what Trump is doing is chipping away at
some of those old assumptions and trying
to create new ones
within this overarching strategy, which
is to realign the world US versus China
for the future.
Um And it's it's because it's not one
thing or another. It's all these
different things. You know, Venezuela is
a perfect example. They went into
Venezuela. Sure, there's some about
symbolic value to it like, you know, the
Chinese were there the same day, right?
That the
raid was launched.
>> yeah.
And then what happened to the oil?
All of a sudden Trump says, "Oh, this
oil we it's under American protection."
And it's not just Venezuelan oil that
can be used to the United States or to
be traded around the rest of the world.
That oil was collateral for loans that
the Chinese made to Venezuela. Now the
Chinese have made loans that are now
uncollateralized or the collateral is
now in the hands of the United States.
That was not an accident. That was
another little piece little bit nugget
that went along with the the overall
strategy. So, I think the message here
just to put this you know, step back in
big picture terms. There is a lot more
going on here than people seem to give
it credit for than certainly those who
say this is about Israel Israel Israel
Israel. I think this is so much less
about Israel than it is everything else
starting with China.
I agree with that point.
Uh it's good to speak to you and you
you're explaining it much better than I
than I can ever do.
Okay.
So, then it
>> What how does Cuba fit into this?
Same thing same thing. Look, I mean, the
Chinese are heavily involved in Cuba.
Um so,
taking out Cuba would be the same thing
as taking out of Venezuela. And
Venezuela is just you know, Cuba is just
the next next logical step after
Venezuela because Venezuela was
basically the economic lifeline to Cuba.
So, when they went into Venezuela, they
also you know, pre-toppled the Cuban
regime by doing so. I I there's a
strategy here. And the strategy is to
fortify the Western Hemisphere first and
foremost, but also to project power
within the hemisphere as well as without
of the hemisphere that says, "Look, this
is the way the world is going to be from
here on. You better get on board with it
because this is the way the world is
going to be from here on."
So, again, that gives
It's like economics. So, we're seeing a
battle of economic warfare, which is
what China uses the Belt and Road
Initiative, investments around the
world, versus military might. So, we're
seeing a clash of these two systems. And
obviously, militarily, you know, that
always beats economics. Economics only
works as long as there's no wars and
there's no warships on someone's coast.
So, that's like a diff- two different
strategies clashing in the world.
Well, the US is also saying we can do
it, too, right? Because the US had long
been, you know, we'll use our economic
might to try to win over the rest of the
world and redraw the lines to our favor.
And kind of, you know, not always, but,
you know, it always kind of reserved the
military option as sort of a last case.
At least that's, you know, the idea.
But, here the Trump administration is
featuring it front and center. Saying,
"Look, we're not afraid to use our
military if we need to in order to
achieve whatever the these objectives
are." So, they're basically bringing out
both fists, you know, they had one fist
behind their back the entire time. Now,
they're saying, "We're going to fight
you with both." Um which again brings me
back to this worry that I have that
there is some level of urgency in the
Trump administration about some kind of
specific threat uh that they were they
were anticipating from China. Maybe it's
a longer-range thing and they're just
trying to um they're trying to get ahead
of it and nip it in the bud before it
goes too far.
>> is right there. It's just rail earth is
a massive thing. It's a massive leverage
card that China has. So, that is that is
a pretty big threat. That could crush
the entire American economy and
military. Yeah, especially as we go
forward here and things get become even
more dicey. Um because, I mean,
economically speaking, you're seeing,
you know, frictions in supply chains
where things don't move the way they
used to be. So, I mean,
in that situation, the Chinese could
exert a a more leverage using smaller
pieces of their what's in their arsenal
Uh than they normally would. So, I agree
with you on that, too. There's this is a
multi-faceted realignment. It's
economic, it's financial, it's it's
political, it's geopolitical, it's
redrawing a lot of different lines and a
lot of different maps. And a lot of
don't you worry what do you worry if
things go wrong
Okay, continue. Sorry, continue. 2020
>> a lot of this is you know started in
2020 with pandemic and response there.
It's just
especially when it comes to the economy.
People don't get that we never really
recovered from 2020 in the pandemic. And
that makes the Chinese never recovered.
The Chinese economy is an utter and
complete disaster that's getting worse
all the time.
Oh,
there's this this idea that the Chinese
are winning everything. That the Chinese
economy is robust and it's strong. It's
absolute opposite. The Chinese are
closer to a banking crisis than they are
to some kind of robust economic boom.
Their banks are riddled with real estate
loans that are
just
non-performing
would be the best categorization.
They're probably non-accrual if not
worse. So, the Chinese have a banking
crisis on their hands. It's a
slow-burning
sort of back-burner banking crisis, but
it's there nonetheless. The economy
stumbled badly in the middle of last
year.
China has been in deflation for pretty 3
and 1/2 years solid, almost solid. 12
straight quarters of deflationary GDP
which undercount the degree of
difficulty they've had to begin with,
which means they produce here, but they
have demand for here. And the only way
to get the two to balance is to cut
prices, which is economically suicide.
So, China is in a very, very difficult
spot economically,
especially without the real estate
bubble to support the rest of the
economy as it was So, what what the US
is this whole strategy is trying to turn
China into a Japan rather than turn
China into a US.
China was never going to become a
western western country. I think that
was a mistake a lot of people made
before 2008. Um ever since Deng Xiaoping
went on his southern tour in 1991 90 Was
91 or 92? I think it was 91. When the
Soviet Union collapsed, the Chinese
realized to avoid becoming the Soviet
Union, we've got to do something
radical. What they did radical was to
allow a limited form of capitalism to
create the wealthy modern society that
socialists have dreamed of ever since
Karl Marx. And so they did that. They
were absolutely successful with it. But
they were never going to commit to
become a neo-western neoliberal western
style nation like that a lot of people
thought they were doing. What they were
doing was riding that wave of wealth to
achieve the socialist dream. The problem
is the socialist dream got interrupted
in 2008 and it led to all sorts of
problems and consequences thereafter.
The Chinese were never going to become
like the United States. They were using
the the their their limited phase of
capitalism to try to to finish off the
socialist revolution and it just got
interrupted. So, the Chinese have always
been moving in the Chinese direction
from the very start. That never changed
even in the 90s and 2000s. So, I think
it's finally it's a positive step that
somebody in the West is finally starting
to admit this. That the Chinese are
doing what the Chinese are doing not
because they're going to join the global
community of nations as we all hold
hands and sing Kumbaya. There are they
have strategic interests that that very
much clash with our own and they always
have. But it was just much easier to get
along when they were doing their
capitalism their limited phase of
capitalism and there was lots of
prosperity in the world, you know,
widespread prosperity in the 90s and
2000s and then um
2010s everything changed and some of
these assumptions were laid bare and
that's what we're dealing with. We're
dealing with the aftermath especially
after COVID the pandemic.
>> Yeah.
What was it we dragged them we accepted
them into
Um my last guest said the reason we
accepted Yeah, we accepted them into the
WTO because of the Iraq war. We didn't
want them to
and in the UN we didn't want them to to
revoke the declaration of war. So what
the the concession that was done by the
US is allowed China to join the
the WTO for China to allow to vote in
the UN for the US to be able to launch a
war in Iraq. So as one of my guests told
me that earlier today, it's like how
it's all connecting. That was one of the
biggest mistakes the US could have could
have made.
Yeah, and it wasn't like the Chinese
were trying to join the brotherhood.
They were using that for their own
specific purposes. They were saying,
"Okay, look, you guys need us for
something, you got to give us something
in return." And what they got was a
period of absolutely epic economic
expansion. The problem is it just it
just got interrupted before they could
complete it, at least from the Chinese
perspective. Which leaves the Chinese in
very bad situation. Because how did
China respond to the 2008 crisis? They
responded by using the Keynesian
textbook. They basically created the
real estate bubble. Because that's what
the Keynesian textbook tells them to do.
When you go into a period of serious
economic uncertainty. I mean, it wasn't
as bad in China as it was elsewhere in
2008. What in 2009 and 2010, really
starting late 2008, the Chinese were
were forced to do the the economic
stimulus. Essentially, they created a
real estate bubble to try to create
enough economic activity to absorb the
shock that they were going to hit from
the Great Recession and its aftermath.
So they created this massive bubble
thinking that the world would get back
on track at some point, but it never
did. So from 2012 onward, the Chinese
have gotten a bigger bigger real estate
bubble with less and less economic
activity to support it. Eventually,
those two those two lines on the map
eventually have to cross and then you're
in Japan territory. So what the Chinese
have been wrestling with, they have this
massive bubble but no way to support it
in real, you know, sustainable economic
growth. What are you going to do in that
situation? Well, their solution was to
use COVID to try to take the air out of
the real estate bubble as slowly as
possible. What it really did is unleash
a banking crisis. And they've been
trying to manage that ever since then.
So for the last 5 years in China,
um it's been real estate problem, real
estate bust, as well as a slow motion
banking crisis. So, the Chinese are in
deep trouble.
If If we link that to the Iran war, so
based on what you're saying, China
cannot afford to give the Strait of
Hormuz control of the Strait of Hormuz
to the US. So, therefore China needs
Iran to be able to beat the US, to be
able to deplete their munitions, exhaust
them politically, financially, exhaust
the world economy. So,
then
>> Or from the other perspective, China has
to let the United States win without
interfering too much to be able to go
back to normal. Because the same rules
apply to China as it does the rest of
the world. If we're talking about a
global energy shock, and the Chinese
economy is already in bad shape to begin
with, there may be more of an economic
and financial downside in China than
there is, say, in the United States. So,
maybe China has an interest in staying
on the sidelines rather than propping up
Iran, and basically kind of surrendering
the Strait of Hormuz to Trump, assuming
that the Trump can get it away from the
Iranians. That may be the strategy that
the administration is using here. Using
the leverage of the weak Chinese economy
and its inability to withstand a
tremendous energy shock.
Hmm.
One could say the meeting between the
first peace negotiations for Iran,
phase one will be Trump and Xi meeting
next week. That will be the first of the
first phase of the Iran negotiations.
>> That's the thing. Don't you think that's
why Trump delayed the meeting? I I To
me, that's one of the reasons why they
delayed the meeting in the first place,
because he wanted to go to Beijing with
from a period of strength or from a
position of strength and say, "Look,
I've got you guys over a barrel here.
I've got you by the balls who is what I
really have here."
Um so, we're going to negotiate I mean,
that's what Trump is. Trump is a
negotiator. He's a deal maker. He
understands um um negotiating from a
position of strength. Whatever you think
about the guy, that's that's how he
operates. So, I think that's the
strategy from the US as it as it relates
to China, to leverage the energy crisis
as you know, as bad as it is in the
United States, and especially Europe and
the rest of the world, Africa, we talk
about food shortage probabilities.
So, there's lots of negative
consequences, but the upside is to
negotiate the Chinese, whatever it is
that's that's on his mind and on his
agenda, from a position of strength.